My Mom Passed Away 10 Years Ago.
Is She in Heaven?
I'm here with my two sisters
to seek your thoughts.
I'll ask on behalf of all three of us.
Next year marks a 10 year anniversary of
our mother passing away
due to a sudden accident.
We performed a Buddhist ceremony
on the 49th day of passing at the temple.
Whenever we face hardships or difficulties
with our in-laws and husbands,
we get together to reminisce
about mother and cry.
During such times I'd pray for
mother's rebirth in heaven.
So I'm curious as to whether
there is such thing as a heaven,
and whether she'd be there waiting for us.
We're hopeful to seek your thoughts today.
(Sunim) That's why the three of you came
all the way here together?
Now repeat after me.
(Questioner) Okay.
Blessed are the believers.
(Sunim) Blessed are the believers.
(Sunim) For theirs is
the kingdom of heaven.
For theirs is the kingdom of heaven.
(Sunim) Blessed are the believers.
Blessed are the believers.
(Sunim) For theirs is
the kingdom of heaven.
For theirs is the kingdom of heaven.
Did that answer your question or not?
(Questioner) But sunim, is that not
what they say in church?
(Audience Laughter)
(Applause)
As a Buddhist, I wanted
to seek your thoughts.
(Sunim) Well, a monk is
telling you now.
(Audience Laughter)
A monk is telling you, not a pastor.
What does "Blessed are the believers,
for theirs is the kingdom of heaven" mean?
Who will benefit from believing that
your mother is in heaven?
(Questioner) I will?
(Sunim) Yes, you will.
How else should I spell this out?
I'm saying that we shouldn't
contemplate over heaven's existence.
She has already
passed away, did she not?
Would it make you feel any good
to think she has gone to hell?
(Questioner) Not at all.
Would it not make you feel empty to think
she has dissipated and is nowhere?
(Questioner) It would.
She doesn't even appear in my dreams.
I wonder where she has gone.
(Sunim) Think to yourself,
'My mother is in heaven.'
Heaven is a much better place
than our world, is it not?
(Questioner) It is.
If it's a better place, isn't it better
that she has reached there already?
(Questioner) It's better that she went.
Then is it better
for her to stay there
or to come back to visit you
time and time again?
(Questioner) But I don't really know
if she's there or not.
(Sunim) Didn't I tell you already?
You said 'There is heaven
for those who believe.' I get it.
(Sumin) Blessed are the believers.
You are tormented
because you don't believe.
So believe from now on, okay?
(Questioner) Okay, thank you.
Would you feel better
to think she's in hell?
(Questioner) No, I wouldn't.
Would you feel better to think
she has dissipated to nothing?
(Questioner) No, I wouldn't.
Would you feel better to think
she remains underground all damp?
(Questioner) No, I wouldn't.
Would it not make you feel better
to think she's living happily in heaven?
(Questioner) It would.
Then is it better that
she remains there or not?
(Questioner) It's better
that she remains there.
Then why are you asking her
to appear in your dreams?
(Applause)
(Sunim) Do you understand?
If you keep missing her,
she'll come back for you.
What happens then?
Even if she comes back,
she doesn't have a body
to come back to, does she?
Then she'll become a wandering ghost.
Do you understand?
(Questioner) So I shouldn't
even be thinking about her?
You can't help thinking
about her, can you?
When a thought comes, let it be.
Just don't overthink it.
Then you'd be calling for her.
Now repeat after me.
(Questioner) Yes.
Farewell mother!
Farewell mother...
(Sunim) Goodbye!
Goodbye...
(Sumin) You should raise
your tone at the end.
Goodbye!
(Sumin) Farewell mother. Goodbye!
Farewell mother. Goodbye!
(Sumin) Good. Let it go, okay?
(Questioner) I will, thank you.
The three of us will go home
with newfound hope.
Thank you.
(Applause)